foreign
[Music]
Comfort measures for serious Advanced
illness has its limitations they're
always some tough cases left with an
unacceptable quality of life despite our
best efforts when suffering cannot be
sufficiently relieved the option of vsed
is a means to shorten life may present a
welcome strategy vscd stands for
voluntarily stopping eating and drinking
which until recently was rarely
discussed as a viable option why is that
the case well historically it's had a
bad rap for good reason
in Nazi Germany patients in Psychiatry
hospitals were starved to death normally
feeding vegetables to patients would be
a good thing but with so few calories
patients died of starvation within a
matter of months
I think the understandable knee-jerk
response from many doctors who have not
witnessed a vsed death it may be to fear
that such a death might be unduly
painful prolonged inhumane but as I
covered in my last video those fears are
not supported by clinical reality it
appears vscd provides most patients with
a peaceful and gentle death that is
generally well tolerated and occurs
within two weeks of beginning the fast
two weeks is still a long time though
Advocates of physician-assisted suicide
where for example a doctor prescribes a
lethal dose of sleeping pills suggests
that's a more Humane option and here's
some poor patient with unbearable
suffering asking their doctor for help
and ending their lives and their
physician it's like too bad storm
yourself to death
but if you're in one of those 42 states
where assisted suicide is illegal what
are doctors supposed to do
thanks to the 14th Amendment patients
everywhere have the right to refuse
Medical Care
yeah but food is different say critics
because it's a necessity but hey look if
people can refuse to be put on a
respirator to save their life then maybe
they should be able to refuse food and
drinks since there ain't nothing more
necessary than breathing Advocates of
the SCD point to the fact that doctors
need not be involved in the decision as
a good thing but clinician support and
management can be critical to provide
Comfort measures for example to manage
the associated thirst which manifests
mostly is just dryness in the mouth you
know we're used to experiencing thirst
when we continue to eat but when both
food and fluids are stopped dehydration
manifests mostly as a dry mouth and you
can trick the brain because there are
water receptors in your mouth that tell
the brain that thirsts is being quenched
even before you swallow so you can
sponge the lips moist in the mouth with
swabs and there's all sorts of
over-the-counter rinses and artificial
saliva you have to be careful about sips
water rice chips though swishing and
spitting may be a better option because
even just small regular sips of fluids
can prolong the process indefinitely
even without excess body fat people
carry around about 150 000 calories
worth of stored energy that's why people
can starve themselves sometimes for
months now I was surprised by the two
weeks without water I mean I thought you
died of thirst in just a couple days
right but that's only if you keep eating
when you burn fat you actually produce
water inside your body like a cup of day
so that's why when you stop drinking and
eating it can take a week or two and
longer if you're sipping water as well
there's some medical side benefits to
the dehydration process you don't have
to worry as much about incontinence or
catheters or bed pans or less nausea and
vomiting is your digestive secretions
dwindle less respiratory secretions
means less coughing and choking and
drowning Sensations a less swelling
which can be a problem with end-stage
cancer and that can relieve pain by
taking pressure off the nerves and
mental awareness May decline which can
bring some relief to suffering patients
as well but can also present a serious
ethical dilemma right at the beginning
when the patient remains cognitively and
decisionally intact right they can
choose to stop any time they want but a
more difficult situation arises later
should patients become delirious and
forget that they ever made the decision
to start asking for something to drink
right on one hand it would seem
unethical to withhold fluids from a
confused thirsty patient to you know
keeps asking for water on the other hand
patients may be upset to find out that
you know after they drink and you know
delirium clears is that they find their
plan didn't work and that indeed appears
to be what happens they feel betrayed by
their caretakers when they're under
strict instruction to not give them food
or drink yeah but are you gonna deny a
confused loved one sustenance if they're
begging for it and if you think that
seems hard denying someone's heart
heartfelt request made days before
imagine if the request was made years
before by its very name voluntarily
stopping eating and drinking right how
do we apply that to the case of dementia
with no effective therapy for
Alzheimer's disease and other
Progressive dementias on the horizon
many reach the final stage of severe
dementia characterized by complete
dependence in all activities of daily
living double incontinence inability to
speak or walk or even recognize family
members and this can go on for many
months or even years it was one of the
reasons why people tend to be more
afraid of developing dementia than
developing cancer
but by then you may be trapped You may
wish to end your life rather than living
on in that state but when the time comes
you can't because you're in that state
so that's why sometimes people diagnosed
with early dementia commit suicide when
they still have the ability to do so but
that deprives them of years of life they
might have otherwise enjoyed
therefore it would be useful to have
available strategy that would definitely
prevent living with a severe case of
dementia for those that feel that way
dementia need not be a trap we can't
while we are still of sound mind right
in advanced directive to withhold food
and water should you ever reach that
state unfortunately most people don't
write anything down and in many cases
even tell their spouses about their end
of life wishes and even if you do write
it down your wishes may not be granted
which is why groups are like end of Life
Choices New York have created specific
Advanced Directive documents to
specifically address the issue of hand
feeding in those with end-stage dementia
but you know be sure to think it through
though right in existence that seems
demeaning and unacceptable to you now
may still be a value to the person you
might become then so should they respect
your prior wishes or your current wishes
withholding food and water from an
incompetent patient who complains of
thirst and hunger could be seen as
itself and affront to basic dignity
thank you
foreign